You have learned how to incorporate velocity and yaw
あなたは 速度とヨー レート
rate measurements into the particle filter.
の測定値を 粒子フィルターに組み込む方法を学びました
But what about sensor measurements, such as readings
レーダーや LIDAR からの読み取り値など センサーの 測定値についてはどうですか
from radar or lidar?
?
These landmark measurements will be
ランドマークの 測定値は
used to compute the update step, which you saw before
更新ステップを計算するために使用され ますが
in the Bayesian filter.
これは ベイズフィルターで見ることができました
Instead of the feature measurements directly affecting
車両状態の 予測に直接的に
the prediction of the state of the car,
影響する特性値を計測する 代わりに
the measurements will instead inform
各パーティクルの 重みを
the weight of each particle.
計測します
The size of each particle in this visualization
この仮想化における粒子のサイズは
correlates with its weight.
重量に関連します
One way to update the weights of the particles
粒子の重量を更新する一つの方法 は
is to use the multivariate Gaussian probability density
それぞれの測定値に対して多変量の ガウス確率密度
function for each measurement and combine
関数を使用し 積を取り すべての
the likelihoods of all the measurements
測定値の確率を 組み合わせる
by taking their product.
方法です
This function tells us how likely
この関数 は
a set of landmark measurements is given our predicted state
ランドマーク測定値のセットが 車両の予想状態に
of the car and the assumption that the sensors have
提供される可能性を示し センサーが ガウス ノイズ
Gaussian noise.
を持っていると仮定します
We also assume each landmark measurement is independent,
また 各ランドマークの測定値は 独立していると仮定します
so we will take the product of the likelihoods
そのため すべての測定値について
over all measurements.
可能性の積を使用します
Here, xi represents the ith landmark measurement
ここでxiは特定のパーティクルに対する i番目のランドマーク計測値を
for one particular particle.
示します
mu i represents the predicted measurement
mu i は ith 測定に対応する
for the map landmark corresponding
地図のランドマーク の予想測定値
to the ith measurement.
を示します
m is the total number of measurements for one particle.
m は 1 個の粒子の 測定数です
And finally, sigma is the covariance of the measurement.
最後に シグマは測定値の 共分散です
The covariance matrix sigma is a symmetric square matrix
共分散行列シグマ は 対称正方行列
that contains the variance, or uncertainty,
であり 変数またはセンサー測定値
of each variable in the sensor measurement,
の各変数の不確実性 と
as well as the covariance, or correlation,
変数間の共分散 または相間
between these variables.
と同様です
In the case of lidar, the variables in question
LIDARの場合、 問題となる変数は、
would be the x and y position of the landmark
ランドマークの x 位置と y 位置、
and vehicle coordinates.
および車両座標です
The diagonal terms of the covariance matrix
共分散行列の対角項 は各変数
are the variance of each variable,
の分散 であり
which is the standard deviation of the variable squared.
変数の 2 乗の標準偏差 です
Here, the orange ovals around each lidar measurement
ここで 各 LIDAR 測定値の周囲の オレンジ色の楕円
are geometric representations of some covariance matrices.
は いくつかの共分散行列の幾何学的表現 です
Notice how the covariance changes as you
対角項を変更すると 共分散がどのように
change the diagonal terms.
変化するかに注意してください
As the x variance term increases,
x 変数 の項が増加すると
the uncertainty in the x direction also increases.
x 方向の不確実性は増加します
Note that feature measurements are usually
特徴の 測定t値
given in vehicle coordinates, where
車両 座標で与えられる
the x-axis points in the direction of the car's heading
x軸は車両の進行方向を示し、
and the y-axis points to the left of the car.
y 軸は 車両の左側を示します
Similarly, as the y variance term increases,
y 変数 の項が増加すると
the uncertainty in the y direction also increases.
y 方向の不確実性は増加します
You can think of the covariance matrix
共分散行列 は重みの逆行列
as an inverse matrix of weights.
と考えることができます
The smaller the diagonal term for a certain variable,
特定の変数に対する 対角線の項が小さければ小さいほど
the more you can trust this variable in the measurement
測定において この変数をより信頼
and the higher the weight we can put on it.
できるようになり 重みが大きくなります
The off diagonal terms of the covariance matrix
共分散行列 の非対角項
represent the correlation between the two variables.
は 2 つの変数間の相関 を表します
For instance, if x increases as y increases,
たとえば x が増加すると y も増加し
you could represent that in the off diagonal terms
この行列の 非対角項
of this matrix.
を示すことができます
For the project, we will assume the different variables
このプロジェクトについて センサー測定のさまざまな変数
in the sensor measurement are independent,
が独立していると 仮定し
and therefore the off diagonal terms are 0.
非対角項が 0 であると仮定します
However, this is often not the case in practice.
しかし これは実用的な ケースではありません
Here is a geometric representation
これは 対角項を除いた
of some covariance matrices with off diagonal terms.
共分散行列の幾何学的表現 です
Notice how the ovals look different from the covariances
楕円が 共分散
before that only had non-zero diagonal terms.
と異なるのは ゼロでない対角項しかないことに注意してください
They now show a positive or negative correlation
x と y の間の正または負
between x and y.
の相関を示します
Awesome.
素晴らしい
After you update the weights for each particle,
各粒子の 重みを更新した後
you will have to resample the particles with probability
前のレッスンで説明したように 重量に
proportional to these weights, as was discussed
比例して 粒子をリサンプリング
in the previous lesson.
する必要があります
And then you're done.
これで 終了です
Next, you'll learn about how to evaluate
次に 粒子フィルター
the accuracy of your particle filter
の正確性を 評価する方法を
once you've successfully built it.
フィルターを 構築してから学習します